So this is some excerpts from
a talk by Ajahn Chah called
right view, the place of coolness.
Just a few
paragraphs.
The practice of Dhamma goes against our
habits. The truth goes against our desires.
The truth goes against our desires.
So there is difficulty in the practice.
Some things which we understand as wrong
may be right.
While the things we take to be right may
be wrong.
Why is this?
Because our minds are in darkness. We
don't clearly see the truth.
We don't really know anything and so are
fooled by people's lies.
They point out what is right as being
wrong and we believe it.
That which is wrong they say is right
and we believe that.
This is because we are not yet our own
masters. Our moods lie to us constantly.
Our moods lie to us constantly.
We shouldn't take this mind and its
opinions as our guide
because it doesn't know the truth.
Is that that's that paragraph done?
Yeah. Well like for example, that's a
very good example of uh
how differently you can take what he
just said.
He said so obviously you can't trust
your moods. You don't have a criteria.
You don't have a right reference point
to know whether you are right and what's
right as right and wrong as wrong as the
Buddha would say.
But most people that I heard they would
be parroting Ajahn Chah would use this
very thing he would say
uh uh
to justify dismissing everything and not
committing to anything cuz everything is
not sure.
But he doesn't say that clearly. He
says, "Yeah, that's your starting point.
You can't trust things until you become
your master and you know right as right
and wrong as wrong."
Yet those same people would be saying,
"Oh, nothing is sure.
Uh you shouldn't trust anything. That's
just opinion. That's just a view." And
then at the same time then develop a
view that there is nothing to be
attained as well cuz of course when
you're dismissing everything there is no
goal for you. There is no there is no um
place that you can sort of achieve
through your efforts. They would then go
beyond the views and you would be the
master of your own understanding.
Yet the suttas that's all they talk
about. And you see Ajahn Chah that's all
he talks about.
So I I like that la- last sentence. We
shouldn't take this mind and its
opinions as our guide.
So you can say that, "Aha, okay." So
"I must not hold to any views."
Failing to see that that is the view you
hold on to.
View of I will not commit to any view.
Yeah, you should not commit to any view
so that you can keep looking for the
right view
but not like I will not commit to any
view as a goal in itself.
Remember even the chant that's done in
the temples in Europe,
"I will not hold to fixed views."
But that's a fixed view in itself.
Refusing to hold to fixed views.
And even the Buddha said that the same
to when the man said, "No view pleases
me." And he and the Buddha told him, "Well
And he and the Buddha told him, "Well
surely that view is pleasing to you. The
one that everything is displeasing to
me." So people think they can just find
a way out of views through through not
committing to any views and that's a
quite a popular belief.
And then they would call people like
Ajahn Chah saying, "And you see how much
misquoting that would be." Cuz he
doesn't say that.
He says your starting point is you don't
know right as right wrong as wrong.
That's what the Buddha genus place. So
you need to make the effort to clarify.
Not make the effort and not commit to
anything because everything is risky and
dangerous.
So I'll continue. It's from
Ajahn Chah.
Some people don't want to listen to
others at all.
But this is not the way of a man
a wise man.
Yeah, okay. Well let me add to that as
well. Like for example
people might think, "Oh no, I have no
problem listening to others."
No, you really want to take that
seriously. It's when
when a person like you ask yourself, "If
I were to to face someone else's view
like say I think this the what practice
is I think it's like this and you do
that and whatever." Now somebody else
comes and challenges that. Or not even
personally challenges me but simply has
a different view.
So you want to ask yourself, "Would I be
affected by that?
Am I threatened? Do I feel I need to
defend myself on account of opposing
views that don't agree with me? Do I
feel I need to justify myself to myself?
Like yeah, I might not get into an
argument with that person but am I
personally affected by the opposing
view? Does it cause a doubt? Does it
make unrest
me experience unrest or similar?
If the answer is yes, that's what it
means. You don't want to hear others.
And that's why you're not wise and
that's why you're not developing wisdom.
Not because you don't go and oh I'll go
and debate with everybody that. No, you
don't learn like that. You learn by
understanding right as right wrong as
wrong. But if you keep protecting whatever you
But if you keep protecting whatever you
got
out of fear of maybe you were wrong
means you won't know wrong is wrong and
right as right cuz you're not committing
to it.
Cuz there's absolutely no reason to be
affected by anything let alone someone
else's view.
To cause emotion arise in you or
anything like that. It's absolutely
no justification for that.
So a wise man listens to everything.
One who listens to Dhamma must listen
just the same whether he likes it or not
and not blindly believe or disbelieve.
He must stay at the halfway mark, the
middle point and not be heedless.
He just listens and then contemplates
and sees the cause and effect for
himself before he believes what he hears. So
before he believes what he hears. So
what does that mean? He listens and
contemplates. He listens and he
understands what that thing is saying. He
what that thing is saying. He
understands the meaning of it. And
that's exactly how he can know whether
it's right or not, whether it's
according to the Dhamma or not.
So how can you understand the meaning of
something if you never make the effort to
if you never make the effort to
understand it?
If your efforts are about not committing
to anything, not holding to any views,
watching your nostrils
how can you then understand that? You
can't. And that's why you don't.
Even if the teacher speaks the truth,
don't just believe it cuz you don't yet
know the truth. You need to understand
it and like not oh you must understand
it for yourself as in now you're going
to have a mystical experience for
yourself. No, you need to understand it.
And if you understand it you will be
able to explain it.
You will be able to put it in words.
Not made it completely inexpressible
idiosyncratic experience that nobody can
relate to it but you know it's my truth.
No, that's the mystical experience.
That's the truth of it.
You won't understand the universal
nature of experience that's in common to
all beings that contain five that are
made of five aggregates which is all
beings. And that's why you'll be free.
And that's why you'll be free.
That's why anyone can relate to it.
Exactly. Yeah.
That's what the Dhamma is is the part
that doesn't change whether it's
revealed or not it stays the same. The
universal principles remain the same.
But it can't be revealed to you if you
if you're not making effort to reveal it
to discern it.
It just cannot be given. Cannot occur
accidentally or spontaneously.
Suddenly you spontaneously develop
wisdom.
Cuz it's quite common to say,
"I feel I know that
Yeah, exactly. I know that I know."
Yeah, I can't put it in words but it was
a real thing. Yeah, it was a real thing
as such.
A real mystical experience. If you can't
put it in words you haven't understood
it. That's why the Buddha would say, "As far
That's why the Buddha would say, "As far
as the language as far as the
designation goes the Tathagata has
understood it."
So I'll continue with the Ajahn Chah
passage. It says most of us have wrong view.
It says most of us have wrong view.
It's just like a maggot.
A maggot lives
living place is filthy. Its food is
filthy. But they they suit a maggot.
But they they suit a maggot.
If you take a stick and brush it away
from its lump of dung
it struggles to crawl back in.
It's the same when the teacher teaches
us to see rightly.
We resist it. Make us It makes us feel
uneasy. We run back to our lump of dung
We run back to our lump of dung
because of that because that's where we
feel at home.
We're all like this.
If we don't see the harmful consequences
of
of our wrong views then we can't leave
them. The practice is difficult so we should
The practice is difficult so we should
listen. There's nothing else to
practice. Yeah, you should listen
Yeah, you should listen
if
if the one that's talking to you knows
what he's talking about.
You shouldn't just listen to somebody
appointed a teacher by the institution
or tradition.
Yeah, good luck with that.
So you should listen but you should also
discern who you listen to.
Because yeah, I mean you can interpret
that bit in the same sense like you know
when somebody comes as a layman to
become a monk sense restraint means I'm
going against my my will. I'm going
against my
my
environment of dung that I used to that
I'm that I was used to.
But the the Ajahn Chah there talks about
the views.
Not just not just
sense restraint.
And and renunciation but the actual
views. And that's that's where the difference
And that's that's where the difference
is. How many people actually actively
challenge their existential views?
How many people like invite on the
existential doubt
in order to uproot it?
And not many.
Many people can live a perfectly
restrained life, and that's very nice.
But that doesn't differentiate you from
a a restrained householder. Right view
does.
But for right view, you just being a
renunciate, that's not enough.
So, how to challenge your view?
How to challenge your views, yeah.
But not play, "Oh, I'll just do what the
teacher says," which is a common
practice in Thailand. "I won't read the
suttas. I won't think for myself. I just
do what Ajahn Chah tells me to do."
Even if that Ajahn is an Ajahn himself,
that's not enough for you to become one.
You can't just do what he tells you to
do. And that's what it said in the the
And that's what it said in the the
um in the before we spoke about it.
Don't just accept it at face value, even
if it's your own teacher.
Yeah, that's the other paragraph.
So, you should listen
if you have a good faith based on your
own discernment that what you're
listening to is correct, then yeah, you
should listen and make the effort to do
it.
It says, "If we have right view,
wherever we go, we are content."
Cuz wherever you go, you're out of
suffering.
So, Ajahn Chah says, "I have practiced
and seen this already.
These days, there are many monks,
novices, and laypeople coming to see me.
If I still didn't know, if I still had
wrong view,
I'd be dead by now.
The right abiding place for for monks,
the place of coolness, is just right
view itself.
We shouldn't look for anything else."
Or is the you know, what I was talking
about is the the sense of safety.
The safe ground. The safe ground.
The right view, it it's not shorter than
that. That's why I keep insisting with people
That's why I keep insisting with people
who are trying to
trying to justify not having a right
view, but but arguing that they're on the
but but arguing that they're on the
right track
of their practice. You can only know
that if you have the right view.
So, until you have a right view, you
shouldn't think you're on the right
track, cuz it will make you complacent
to that extent.
And that's that's exactly what Ajahn
Chah is saying there.
The only place of safety and coolness is
the right view. There is no lower than
that. So, if you're able to go lower than
So, if you're able to go lower than
that, you can expect to be even lower
than that.
So, you should really be aiming for
higher than that.
At least get a right view then as a
result of it.
Finish this quotation. Yeah. Finish it.
So, can can I just come back to that
first one when he said that we should
not trust our moods? Mhm.
But you know, our moods are also like
part of our experience.
Yeah, not trusting not trusting the
moods doesn't mean denying them.
Means not acting out of them.
In order to act out of your mood, you
must have taken it for granted. Same, in
order to act out of sensuality, you took
it at a face value. In order to act out
of ill will, you took it at a face
value. You trusted
So, not trusting it doesn't mean, "Oh, I
I'm not accepting this." Means I don't
act out of it.
Means I'm aware of it in its in its
persistence, basically, for what it is.
And I'm not trusting it to make me act
and do things out of it.
And that's how the another thing that
people keep quoting on and that
everything is teaching us. That's how
everything teaches you, because of your
attitude in regard to everything, not
because everything is actually teaching
you.
Which basically again brings that thing
that we must put the effort to
understand or the practice that the
teaching is about. Nature of things
means anything
that takes in that nature. If you're
discerning the nature, means anything
will be pertaining partaking in your
discernment.
When you say basically when you say like
uh you don't if you don't have right
view, you don't know. But this can
actually put everyone who has no right
view in the position of like you know, I
I don't know.
So, and then he can he can be or that
person can be like uh uh
uh
you know, not confident actually to
express anything, to do anything, and
just trying to follow someone because he
would always say, "You know, I don't
know. I still don't have right view."
Yeah, but following following someone,
that person would be fully aware that I
have no right view.
So, following someone on account of me
not having a right view has nothing to
do with me not having the right view or
having the right view.
In other words, they would not be
justified in following someone. It
wouldn't make them follow someone. Yeah,
but what I mean is more like, you know,
then there can be a person who is just
claiming, "Yes, I have right view." And
all these unconfidential
people who don't have right view would
just go and follow him. Yeah, but that's
go and follow him. Yeah, but that's
because they don't have the right view.
Yes, that's exactly.
But that's not what I'm saying.
That's not what this is saying, either.
That's just quite the opposite. Someone
else's right view doesn't do anything
for you.
That's even what what the first quote
said. Even if it's your own teacher, as
in somebody who doesn't know what he's
talking about, you must investigate
that. Don't just follow it. Don't just
take it. I But the person who is like
following the teaching of the Buddha, he
has basically right view. No, sotapanna
has the right view. Yeah, but you have
also this lokiya right view, this
ordinary right view. Yeah, but
you are not ariya, so you actually know
the right view.
It's a right view, but ordinary right
view. right view.
right view.
I'm talking about sotapanna freedom from
suffering. Mundane right view doesn't
free you from suffering.
But it's still kind of right view.
Well, no, it's a right it's a it's a
right basis for the right view of the
sub the the right view that matters is
the sotapanna's right view.
Obviously, it doesn't mean that lay
right view doesn't matter. Means you
can't have sotapanna's right view
without the mundane right view. But
mundane right view, you're still a
puthujjana. And the sense of safety starts with
And the sense of safety starts with
sotapanna.
Yes. Not with puthujjana. So, mundane
right view is not the sense of safety.
Okay, so we are speaking about this
ariya right view, not the ordinary.
Okay. That's what we said.
That's what we said.
And also, we can speak about the mundane
right view, and you realize most people
don't Most monks don't even have it, not
even mundane right view,
despite being in robes for 40, 50 years.
You think so? Oh, most certainly. Cuz if
you start thinking about the mundane
right view, you realize it's already
quite an accomplishment in undoing lots
of wrong views.
It's quite a lot of self-transparency
developed through mundane right view.
Yes. Recognition of the nature of things
through mundane right view. And when you
hear the the the other people, monks,
whatever, speaking, you realize they
don't even have that basic recognition
of those views. Yes. And so, please, can
you actually speak about this mundane
right view, you know?
Well, well, we spoke before. Remember? I
think I think it was with you that I
spoke about the authenticity and
self-transparency. Yes, that's what you
spoke about.
what it is.
Like recognition of the validity of the
recognition of the validity of the
arisen phenomena.
There is given. There is There is There
There is good. There is bad. There is
mother. There is father. There isn't
There isn't the fact that I don't know
something. Yes. There is the There is
next life. There is this life. Again,
all these things is basically
recognition of the state of mind as it
is, not coming out of a view that you have
not coming out of a view that you have
preconceived.
As in, there is rebirth cuz I believe in
it, not because I see it. Or, there is
no rebirth cuz I don't believe in it,
not because I see it. Mhm.
But you recognize it, "I don't know."
So, first bit for me, it's not there is
rebirth, there isn't. There is lack of
knowledge. Yes. That's a factual thing,
and you recognize it as an arisen thing.
Yes. And you know, like people might say,
And you know, like people might say,
"Yeah, there is mother, there is
father." But if you were to ask them,
they would jump onto the view of modern
science and medicine explaining that
it's just a bunch of molecules and
electrons and there's nothing in reality
is real. Everything is constantly
changing. So, you see that fully
committed Buddhist people and
practitioner undermine the basic reality
of the world that they did experience
themselves in their You can't like avoid
it. But you can certainly misinterpret
it with your view, which means they
don't even have a mundane right view.
Yes. Cuz their views deny the basic
mundane aspects of their experience.
And that's what it means, there is
mother, there is father. Like, no,
mother is mother. That's it. There is no
lower threshold than that in your
experience. Uh-huh.
But people might talk about it on some
occasion, but fundamentally, their view
would be like an external assumption of
a scientific world, for example, which
says, "Well, in reality, we are just,
you know, nothing's real. That's why
everything is constantly impermanent."
But it's nothing to do with Buddhist
teaching whatsoever. No, there is
mother, there is father. That's your
That's your threshold. That's your
starting point. Then the impermanence
you discern within that is that
impermanence of ownership, impermanence
of of appropriation, impossibility to to
kind of be a controlled master of
things, cuz they have arisen on their
own. And then you realize, "I, it's the
impermanence of my sense of self, not
impermanence of a random sto- stone,
tree, table, and so on."
Yes. And how many times, I bet you heard
yourself people say that, "Yeah, modern
science is proving that the Buddha was
correct cuz everything is constantly
changing." And you hear that from very,
very senior, established monks
in their talks and whatnot. So, you
realize, "Yeah, you can be in robes for
the rest of your life, 100 years, and
still not even have a mundane right
view, let alone suffering and all that."
let alone suffering and all that."
But it's no one else's fault.
You are always solely responsible for
the views you hold.
So, recognize of
like of of things arising on their own, to
of of things arising on their own, to
what extent they arise. Recognition of
things as phenomena, if you want to call
it that way. Not jumping to material
explanation, not mystified
in the ideological explanation, but
literally just no, this is the
experience of having a mother.
This is the experience of having a
father. This is the experience of doubt.
This is the experience of sensuality.
Already we draw from that material
content of it that we are all so focused
on. And that is a necessary basis for really
And that is a necessary basis for really
discerning the signs of your mind as
phenomena. Because that's the problem.
Having these views prevent you from
seeing your mind as a thing that has
arisen. And that is an absolute prerequisite for
And that is an absolute prerequisite for
the right view as the Buddha said,
chetana nimitta. Without it, you can't
have the right view. I see. So, how can
you see your mind as an enduring thing
when obviously enduring things you deny
with your own view?
So, you need the mundane right view to
get used to it and then to start seeing
things that matter. Mind, feeling,
intentions. On the level of enduring things.
On the level of enduring things.
That's where many people struggle with
those three characteristics that the
Buddha describes. Arising is manifest,
ceasing is manifest, persisting while
changing is manifest. People read it,
but they always keep saying and keep
holding the view, arising is manifest,
persisting while changing is manifest,
ceasing is manifest.
So, they change the order cuz for them
it's all seen in a third person of me
observing something lasting and then
disappearing. But it isn't.
Arising is manifest.
Ceasing is manifest.
Persisting while changing is manifest.
And that's already something that's not
linear in the way people are used to.
Because if if linear observance is
required for you to understand
impermanence, all you need to do is wait
for your body to die. Death will be the
enlightenment. But it isn't. Cessation
is another another arising, another
manifestation. But for people cessation means the
But for people cessation means the
impermanent. It doesn't.
And that's what the Buddha said millions
of times. Arising is manifested.
Ceasing is manifested.
Either way, thing endures and that
enduring is also manifested, persisting
while remaining the same.
relates to this like there is mother
Exactly. father is
A certain threshold that you don't
overly kind of um
overly determined with your
interpretation of science and medicine,
but you don't go the other way and then
mystify and say everything is constantly
whatever. No, you recognize there is the arising.
No, you recognize there is the arising.
It's manifested. Oh, there is the
experience of cessation. It's manifest.
Either way, things are enduring. Yes.
Either in the form of arising or
ceasing, they're enduring. And that's
manifested as well. Yes.
And we are basically caught in this
manifestation. You can't
That is the You can't step outside of
it. You can't Exactly. The problem is
you assuming the external point of view
to it, which ultimately is what attavada
is, assuming the external self to this
whole thing.
So, you basically can't step outside of
manifestation. what That's what defines wrong view as a
what That's what defines wrong view as a
wrong view, a view that contradicts the
fundamental universal aspect of your
experience. That's why the Buddha did
not invent the right view, did not
invent the dhamma, he just discerned it
on the right terms.
But yeah, for that you need instruction.
You can't accidentally arrive at it cuz
everything points in the wrong
direction.
The mundane right view
properly anchors you isn't it like in
the sense that
mom and dad you you you
you only know them there as in like
you can't go back and ex- like remember
seeing mom, dad for the first time in
your birth or something.
that's what I mean.
Uh mundane right view recognizes the the
the uh
the the basis
of the arisen experience as a starting
point. Yeah, like See, like you have the
arisen experience of emotionally charged
experience of of your your father
getting sick or something.
That is the base That is the starting
point. But you see, even most people's
practice is about covering that up,
denying it, removing it. Why? Cuz it
bothers me.
So, then my practice becomes management
of what bothers me.
And you manage it through the wrong
views. You manage it through saying
well, fundamentally it's just a
collection of atoms and what That's
another way of saying fundamentally
there is no father.
In reality there is no father. It's just
my attachment that the father is there.
But it isn't.
Your father is there. That's your
starting point.
And if you start thinking like that,
then your practice of dhamma cannot be
the management. It can only result in
uprooting of the problem in the first
place.
If your practice is secondary, means
it's management, which means it's not
the dhamma, even if you do the dhamma on
account of it.
But now you have no leeway of denying
the fatherhood
experience of there is a father.
The experience of there is a mother. The
experience there is experience of doubt.
Oh, I don't know that.
Those are the arisen, factually
enduring, present states of your mind.
And if you stop denying it, then you all
you realize the only way to not be
bothered by it is to uproot the craving
towards towards the feeling as in remove
the suffering. Not through saying
everything is already impermanent, thus
I shouldn't suffer. Or it's just a
collection of flesh, organs, and
constantly moving electrons, there is no
father. Through denying it, you try to find a
Through denying it, you try to find a
way out of what bothers you.
And that that's what I mean. It's it's
management of the fact that you're
bothered in the first place. But if you
do dhamma rightly, you can't be bothered
in the first place. Then there is no
reason for you to deny your father,
mother, divine realms, whatever. There
is no reason. Why would you? The only
reason people deny it is cuz they don't
know other way of other way out of
suffering.
And Bhante, what about this experience
of kamma vipaka? We don't have this
experience. Yeah, see, that's another
thing. The Buddha never said like you
must figure it He actually said thinking
about kamma vipaka will result in
distraction or madness.
But that's what you recognize.
I don't know to what extent my actions
will bear fruit. That's your fact That's
your factual experience right there and
then. So, how would you act then? If you're
So, how would you act then? If you're
not dismissing kamma, or if you don't
have like a perfectly cut kind of
template of how kamma works, you
realize, oh crap, I don't know.
So, I better be really really careful
because even when I think I might be
doing good,
I don't know for myself.
So, it's not worth the risk.
And it's same when when people ask him
about the next life and the Buddha said,
well, the the truth is you don't know.
That's your starting point. But you
reflect, I don't know, so I better act
in the best case scenario in the worst
case scenario just in case they did is
true, it's going to be too much to handle.
it's going to be too much to handle.
So, I assume there is cuz it will make
me act carefully. Either way, win-win.
Yes, win-win situation.
And also it's basically win-win
situation because you are preparing the
ground for arising of this supermundane
Absolutely. Yeah. Absolutely.
Cuz without it mundane you can't
No, the the only reason people don't
have the even mundane right view is
because they haven't taken up
responsibility for their own existence.
Yeah. You like As I said, you can be perfectly
You like As I said, you can be perfectly
restrained monk for 60 years and still
have not taken responsibility for your
existence. Now you have tradition doing the
Now you have tradition doing the
responsibility for you. Vinaya doing the
responsibility for you. Form doing the
responsibility for you.
You must take it on.
You must do it.
Which initially is going to result, oh,
so I could then decide to not do it.
Literally, a whim of thought can uproot
your whole existence and that's very
very scary.
So, then you just move one from one
authority placing on to next authority
until eventually you go into the
authority of old age, senile experience
of like, you know, not being bothered by
anything cuz you can't remember half of
the things and then you say, oh, old age
is so graceful and peaceful.
Cuz you know, sexual desire doesn't
bother you cuz it just went completely
dormant and you can't even bother
thinking about it.
So, good luck
uprooting anything at that stage if you
haven't up- uprooted things when they
were obvious,
when you could have developed
transparency, you're not going to do it after
you're not going to do it after
hammering them down with like decades of
habits of wrong views.
What do you think is the balance between
like you know, we can we have to
obviously face doubts cuz we don't know
everything. What's the difference between like
What's the difference between like
getting kind of
uh steered around by those doubts and
you kind of just start
going the other way versus using your
doubt in a way that can be useful? Well,
the difference is whether you're aware
of the presently enduring nature of the
doubt. Like you can you doubt the content of
Like you can you doubt the content of
something, but you can't doubt the
experience of doubt being present.
Yeah. So, the the best way
So, the the best way
to withdraw yourself from any
involvement with content of your
experience is the doubt.
That's why Sartre's being and
nothingness starts basically being
becomes revealed when you put yourself
in question.
You start questioning your own
existence, that's it. That's how you
arrive at your own existence.
Through questioning it.
Not like
academically, genuinely. I am, but I
could have not been.
Immediately withdraws you from the
entire content.
If you understand the nature of that,
means you have fully transcended any
form of pull that content can exercise
over you.
Cuz you can doubt this, you can doubt
that, but you can't doubt the experience
of the present. There is no doubt in
regard to this content.
And that's exactly what the Buddha said,
"The best of the worst of the wrong
views is that one
um
I could have I could have been No, it
could have been it could have not been
for me. It will not be." Literally
withdrawn from any content, any
possibility of the content. And if you
would let go of that, that's
arahantship. But for that, you would need the right
But for that, you would need the right
view.
But still, it's a good thing even if
with with with the wrong view to develop
it cuz it already primes you very
closely to the right view. You already
are on the level of recognizing
universal aspect of the enduring
experience not being pulled by the
content of it.
So, sometimes doubt will affect you
more, doubt will affect you less, but
you will know that you're more or less
on the right track if you remain aware
of the present enduring doubt as a state
of mind.
What I've been trying to think about
when things like all these kinds of
states, doubt, frustration, despair,
trying to think about things like
it's a question of
but am I am I how bothered am I by it
first place. And it's in your mind tells
you that like it's almost like you're
obligated to be bothered. Like if you're
not bothered, you're not doing the
effort. I must Yeah, exactly. I must I must do
I must Yeah, exactly. I must I must do
something. Yeah. But then it's like what
if not being bothered by this is the
effort? So, you're not dismissing it. You're not
So, you're not dismissing it. You're not
denying it. Oh, there is no doubt. There
is nothing. There is no mother. There is
no father.
But at the same time, you're
recognizing, "Okay, it has a reason.
It's real to that extent."
But now the choice is on me to give in
to the craving towards the content or
not. And that's how you find that middle
And that's how you find that middle
ground.
Denying it, completely dismissing it,
not through completely giving in to it
and and and following it sort of
off the course.
The part that's mundane right view
at the end of that passage.
It says there are those who have
realized for themselves direct knowledge
and declare this world and the other
world. So, there there are those who
have realized. Yeah, who know.
That's mundane right view. So, you you
know that
it's possible. Well, the extent the
extent of the possibility. Why? Because
again, that possibility even for most
people even their their own thoughts
would be regarded as something that's
not real.
Cuz you know, cuz they're used to
substance. Their view the level of being
the level of proliferated consciousness
is on the level of substance. So, when
their thoughts are there in the
background, it's usually, "Oh, that's
not even real."
But the fact that you can call it not
real means there is something that can
be called not real, which means that
thing is real.
So, your view of this is not real or
it's less real, it's a complete
contradiction in terms.
So, you completely undo that, you will
recognize that possibilities are real as
such. And to that extent, you understood that
And to that extent, you understood that
extent.
Of this world, of the next world,
of the current world or all the possible
worlds.
So, coming to the knowledge that oh,
it's possible Someone says it's possible
to be free from Yes, I Exactly.
So, that possibility is present in
everyone's experience right here, right
now. And always is, always was.
And always is, always was.
And will be as well. And what do you do?
Exactly. Oh,
so there is mother, there's father.
There's it There is the possibility of
freedom. There is the possibility of the right
There is the possibility of the right
view. There is the possibility of
arahantship. So, you have this No, there's no there's
So, you have this No, there's no there's
no possibility. Well, that's what I
mean. Usually, almost automatically,
that's what I said when you read the
previous passage. You start denying this
basic um basic uh manifestation of things,
um basic uh manifestation of things,
you start justifying it with through
external views, you will automatically
arrive at the view of there's nothing to
be attained anyway or nothing can be
really attained.
Cuz I heard my monks many different
monks difference in the order of things,
difference in the order of things,
whatever, just openly say those things
when I'm a seat. No, no, no, don't worry
about So, that's just that's just more
attachment. There's nothing to be
attained. The more you practice, the
less you know.
Like well, maybe your practice makes you
more ignorant, but not not what the
Buddha was teaching. Not what Ajahn Chah
was teaching for Christ's sake.
Like you read this passage, it's quite
clear. Yeah, don't take it for granted. Don't
Yeah, don't take it for granted. Don't
dismiss it.
Understand it, and then you'll know it
at least to that extent. Then take it
further if it's not sufficient. But ah, okay.
if it's not sufficient. But ah, okay.
Nothing can be trusted. Ah, okay. I
don't trust anything. That's my view
now. That's what pleases me. And uh what
sort of I'm No, no, there's nothing to
be attained anyway.
That's it.
That's what I mean. Naturally, through
denial of that nature, you're going to
deny everything, and you're not even You
won't even feel responsible for not
becoming a sotapanna.
You okay with it? And do you think there
is a connection maybe between the two?
Oh, it's too hard to do it. Let me
dismiss it. Don't feel obliged to do it.
You're like sour grapes.
Yeah. Yet even the the the the Ajahn Chah
Yet even the the the the Ajahn Chah
himself
said if you're not if you don't have the
right view within the first 5 years,
you're wasting your time.
Oh, but no, there's nothing to be
attained. But I follow Ajahn Chah. But
there's nothing to be attained.
There's no sotapatti, nothing. But I
also follow the Buddha, and I'm a
Buddhist monk.
But again, there's nothing to be
attained.
That's what I mean. It comes down
Mundane right view comes down to
accepting that responsibility. Yes. Cuz
there is mother there is there is
possibility of enlightenment. Oh,
so it's my possibility of enlightenment.
It's possibility of my awakening. And
you also know your So, I'm not So, I'm
responsible for it then. Yeah. So, there
is a possibility to be free.
I'm perfectly
free to choose to not go that way. But
that means I will be responsible for not
getting the results of it. Yes. And
that's the first thing that hit me when
I started believing in the suttas as a
layman. When the Buddha said, "There is
When the Buddha said, "There is
suffering. There is freedom from it.
Come and see for yourself."
And I remember cuz I couldn't even find
anybody say that.
And now I found somebody said it.
And I remember it was finally somebody
said it, and I felt it like
I don't have to follow it.
Now I know there is, but I could go the
other way.
But immediately, I felt like, "Okay. So,
if I choose to not become a monk and
practice this,
I'm fully responsible for whatever
happens to me for the rest of my life
even if it's not my fault in lay terms."
Mhm. There is the world. There is freedom
There is the world. There is freedom
from the world. You choose the world
means you choose everything else that
might come on account of that world.
It's based on that choice of you not
renouncing it.
And that I couldn't ignore that. I could
not ignore that fundamentally then I'm
responsible even for complete
things that completely out of your
control cuz you chose to stay in the
domain where things out of your control
can happen. Good or bad, doesn't matter.
So, recognizing that there is the
enlightenment, there is my
enlightenment. My possibility.
My possibility.
And how can somebody without
acknowledging that
existence of possibilities
without reverting to some explanatory
third-person wrong view, how can then he
take that on as his practice? He can't.
His practice is going to have a magical
connection to the result.
Oh, I'm devotional. I'm this. I'm doing
that. I respect tradition. I I meditate
3 hours a day. I watch my nostrils. I
watch the soles of my feet, and then
enlightenment will happen to me on
account of these observances and duties
that I do.
No, enlightenment cannot happen. You can
only develop it. In order to develop it,
you need to know what it is.
And how can you what How can you know
what it is when you're even denying the
basic possibility of it being in the
first place?
So, yeah, my mundane view is very
important.
But it's not to be confused A lot of
people would say that I
it's not possible for me
Yeah. enlightenment in this lifetime.
Yeah, that's what you need to say like
unless you feel it's your duty to become
a sotapanna, you will never do it.
It's a hard thing to do, and the only
way to do it is through full acceptance
of responsibility for not doing it,
which would be more unpleasant than
trying to do it.
And that's how you do it.
So, it's your duty to become
to be free from suffering.
Yeah. Uh-huh. Not duty, responsibility.
Your responsibility, yeah.
Yeah, it's your respon- Your respon- If
you're not free from suffering, it's
it's it's on you.
If you're free from suffering, it's also
on you. So, you have a choice.
No complaints. No. No. No, no.
Blaming. Yes.
Yeah, that's good that you said this.
Yeah. It's your responsibility if you stay in
It's your responsibility if you stay in
the realm of Mara,
it's your responsibility whatever
happened to you.
You know, whatever kind of suffering.
Wait. And you'd be surprised how much
people don't want to hear that.
So, it's like, "No, you can stay a
layman. Whatever happens to you,
Whatever happens to you,
literally, it's your fault. If you want
to blame somebody, you can only blame
yourself. If you want to blame somebody for
If you want to blame somebody for
enlightenment, you can only blame
yourself. And many people don't even want to admit
And many people don't even want to admit
that cuz it's too unpleasant.
It is.
And that's exactly admit there are there
there there is my action. There are results of
there is my action. There are results of
my action. I Oh, my responsibility. My
results. To the extent of infinity, who knows?
To the extent of infinity, who knows?
That domain, it just goes Who knows? I
have no idea, which means
it's not worth the risk then, isn't it? You said
You said
There are some people who say that uh
I I cannot become arahant in this
lifetime because of my karma.
Yeah. My past moment my bad karma. Yeah.
I know. Uh people say that because
they talk about kind of factually.
That they they would only work
if you genuinely develop your mind to
the extent of seeing your past actions.
Like if I ask you if I come and slap you
in the face because yesterday you came
and you stole my I don't know my
property. You you say okay well I deserved it.
You you say okay well I deserved it.
Why? Because you have a memory of it.
If you done something 10 years ago and
somebody remind you of it you still say
okay yeah I done that.
But now people try to sort of use karma
as an excuse for not doing anything not
having memory of it as well. So I don't
remember what I've done but I choose
that lack of memory to be my excuse for
not doing something now that I'm fully
aware of I can do.
So I'm saying it wouldn't work even if
you were to have a memory of it let
alone when you don't have a memory of
it. Because if that's your karma from before
Because if that's your karma from before
it's the same karma from yesterday as in
what you done yesterday is your karma
what you done 10 years ago is your
karma. So why stop there?
So why stop there?
Oh maybe there are things that I've done
10 lifetimes ago and they will be as
much as mine as what I've done yesterday
is mine.
And that's exactly point they will be.
Nobody they can't be anyone else's.
But you choose to draw this invisible
line where your memory is oh I don't
remember not my problem.
No you won't actually go the other way.
I don't remember that's it's a big
problem. Like things I don't remember in this
Like things I don't remember in this
life that I can you know end up paying
price of somebody remind me of I had a
problem. Imagine things that you don't
remember from previous lives.
How much of a problem they would be?
So instead of using the lack of memory
for kind of not feeling responsible with
it should be the other way. Lack of
memory should make you responsible for
everything. Even if you have no memory of what it
Even if you have no memory of what it
is.
But that's very unpleasant for the mind
that wants to deny it.
That's not giving up the view of denying
it.
Cuz you would feel responsible for
something you done like oh today I do
this cuz 10 years ago I started like I
don't know
developing certain habit.
But you can't deny responsibility for it
cuz you still have a memory of it.
But you deny responsibility because yeah
maybe you you can't practice properly
because of your previous karma. Your
previous karma.
Your previous action. So you yourself
are responsible for you yourself not
being able to practice today.
That responsibility whether it's from 10
years ago 10 lifetimes ago doesn't
matter it's yours as much as as always
will be.
So I can't become an arahant because of
my previous karma means
uh I can't become an arahant because I
can't become an arahant.
That's the reason in itself.
And that is
that is the reason.
But we kind of
creating the loop of all karma memory
you kind of obscure your responsibility
for it.
Yeah and I think it's probably also
connected what you said before with this
observances. Oh yeah. The person is
following some kind of observances some
kind of practice without results.
Yeah. I mean this kind of results so then he
I mean this kind of results so then he
would end up with this kind of excuse
you know. Cuz he was maybe meditating
he's been meditating 20 30 years. So
they would end up they would end up with
an excuse that relieve uh
relieves them of responsibility not the
excuse of wait a minute maybe I've been
doing it wrong. Yeah.
Oh no I couldn't have been doing it
wrong cuz that would mean my efforts
were wasted but that's too unpleasant to
admit. So instead I'll just dismiss it. Yeah.
So instead I'll just dismiss it. Yeah.
I'll just say well no I'm doing
everything right.
But But I can't get to it because of
something in the past they have no
memory of it. So something they have no
memory of it
means it doesn't exist for you. Yet that
which doesn't exist for you you have no
knowledge of no memory no perception of
it you use as a presently perceived
reason for your failure.
I mean you see how wrong that is.
Other deeply rooted self decep act of
self deception.
what you are saying because just
recently I heard about one well known
teacher who would openly admit
he's puthujjana
and he can't in this life because of
this previous karma achieve
anything but he is a well known teacher
and he can teach others still to
practice So here I am They can by his advices
So here I am They can by his advices
because they are not bothered by that
karma he has. Sure sure sure because his
advice is obviously on the level of
mechanical instruction
that anybody can do or not.
But that's if if you have a view that
that's what dhamma practice is then yeah
anybody can be the teacher.
But that's not what the dhamma is isn't
it? Because as we explained the mundane
view requires you to take on
responsibility which is not cannot be
done mechanically.
Like you can do go through the same
motions as I do but your attitude is
attitude of not accepting
responsibility. So I can give you verbatim instruction
So I can give you verbatim instruction
it won't work cuz your attitude doesn't
work which means there's no dhamma
there. So you going through these motions is
So you going through these motions is
going through the literal motions
without the dhamma.
And that's what sila bata paramasa means
it doesn't mean rituals and rites and
whatnot so things that are obviously
ridiculous when it comes to practice. Means virtue
when it comes to practice. Means virtue
sila and duty sense of duty. So it's my
duty to sit cross legged and meditate as
a
Yeah but why you do it? To what extent
does it help you? Do you understand why
you're doing it? No I'm just doing it.
It's my duty to do this and my virtue is
also my duty and that's a fetter.
So how can you abandon that fetter
without abandoning your virtue?
Without abandoning your efforts.
And and that's that's what
differentiates it. See if it's a duty
means you bypass responsibility at least
a little bit. You know I'm a judge. It's
my duty to pass a judgment onto you.
As in I'm not responsible for sending
you to jail.
It's like well you chose to be the judge
which is the one who sends people to
jail. So you introduce the proxy to cover up
So you introduce the proxy to cover up
the fact that you are the one condemning
people to die or not.
Oh but it's my duty. Why is it? Well
because I need a job. Why do you need a
job? Because I have a family. Why do you
have a family? Because you had sex with
your wife.
Was that also your duty?
It wasn't. So you done things you wanted
to do and now you're refusing to accept
responsibility for it. I have to work.
Yes cuz you have six children.
Generally it would be your duty if
somebody forced those children on you
and you had to look out even then it
wouldn't be your duty. You would be
responsible or rather you would be free
to accept it or not.
And that's that scary bit. Literally no
matter which way your life went what you
which way your life went what you
invested in it one morning you can wake
up and decide to just and leave all.
Yes it's your responsibility. And having
that that edge present all the time
freaks people out.
Because the mind is undeveloped the mind
is unrestrained the mind has no basis of
virtue and and self control. So
just that a sight of the edge makes the
mind Yeah that's a probably
run in terror. The most like scary scary
thing to accept your responsibility for.
That's the most scary thing for monks
when they are ordained like like my duty
my duty my virtue I must do this vinaya
vinaya and getting extremely neurotic
whereby it's not even vinaya anymore
it's just some obscure ridiculous
interpretation upon interpretation. Well
the rule is clear context is clear
everything is clear but
a person can't sleep for 5 days just cuz
mind is like oh what if what if what if.
Cuz through avoiding responsibility you
actually make things worse for yourself.
They can overwhelm you and whenever
whenever circumstances present
themselves in that way.
Initially it's going to be much more
unpleasant to accept responsibility for
your virtue like no I am choosing to do
this. I am choosing it will then enable
you to draw a line as well.
To to the mind infected with doubt and
mara and everything else. No I will not
think that because I know exactly what's
right and even those people know exactly
what's right. But because they're
projected in this third person view of
duty something that must be done that's
nothing to do with me then they also
keep needing the third person's
confirmation and affirmation of what
they're doing to be right.
That's why the doubt can only be settled
by going around and asking people and so
they tell you what you want to hear.
By reading reading reinterpreting
reinterpreting until you get what you
want to hear by having everybody else
does the same rites and rituals you do
cuz if they don't it will question the
validity of the stuff you do.
Everything is out there nothing is in me
nothing is my responsibility. That's why
those people would genuinely be upset
existentially threatened if you wear
your sabong differently.
Or here we wear flip flops he doesn't
wear flip flops mind already panic cuz
there is there is a different way about
this which means it's not a duty then
the way I took it to be.
No in this tradition we wear our robe
like this and we put our cups down like
this. Okay well I'm part of this tradition and
Okay well I'm part of this tradition and
I put my cup like this.
That's it meltdown.
Cuz their practice is out there. Well
this is what must be done which means
this is what must be done by everyone.
Cuz if they don't do it then I realize
I'm responsible for keep assuming that
this is what must be done. So it brings
you back onto that personal
responsibility that you wanted to avoid
in the first place which is why you
latched onto that fetter of duty and
virtue. Yes. So there is no dhamma without sila
Yes. So there is no dhamma without sila
but dhamma is not the sila.
And as regards the sila bata paramasa
can we say so as I understand it's
basically about this attitude. So when
you change that attitude you remove just
paramasa but that sila and mara
Exactly exactly. Like yeah so the one
that doesn't abandon his sila to become
a sotapanna as in he starts doing the
opposite. So outwardly you maybe don't
So outwardly you maybe don't
you don't see any difference in behavior
of that person.
Absolutely, yeah. But that person who is
fully projected in that external third
person view, they can't see that. For
them saying "Dhamma is not sila." means
"So, I must not keep sila then."
Literally. If you say that sila battaparamasa is is
If you say that sila battaparamasa is is
a fetter of you assuming this is my duty
and virtue by doing so avoid personal
responsibility for it, for them that
means "Okay, so I I should disrobe and
go and you know find a wife and and so
on." No. Doesn't mean that at all.
Sila remains unchanged.
But your attitude is now changed. It's
not you doing it anymore on account of
the external assumed authority or
whatever. You're doing it cuz you see it
exactly as a necessary basis for
discerning the the nature of phenomena
of your mind, feelings, and intentions,
which you now understood is the way out
of suffering. Yes.
So, unless that responsibility is taken
on for doing it in the first place, even
the wrong things you're doing, even the
fetters you hold, you can't uproot them.
Cuz if you deny that is a fetter,
you cannot undo that fetter cuz you're
not seeing it.
What would be another translation of
that silabattaparamasa?
What is I think virtue and duty is a
good translation. But not
non-responsibility in virtue.
Oh, yeah, yeah, sure, sure, sure. Or
casting off your responsibility.
Right, right, yeah. Well, virtue and
duty as a basis of you avoiding
responsibility for virtue and duty. Mhm.
But sila But it can be also like a
behavior. You know, that's the one meaning of
You know, that's the one meaning of
Yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, yeah, yeah,
behavior, sure. Cuz it can have also
micchasila. Yeah. Mhm.
And maybe also we can say like that
micchacara, it can be also about
responsibility that you are basically
casting off your responsibility for
right view. Well, fundamentally, yeah,
all of the hindrances are taken same
centrality. Ill will.
And now came actually a question So, we
have that first fetter
sakkayaditthi. But it seems that basically craving
But it seems that basically craving
and this craving, hate, and yeah, that
craving is still present
even in that person with
Yeah, sakkayaditthi is is is on that
level of it's it's attavada. It's on the
level of that view. So, what what frees
you? What is that freedom of
breaking through this sakkayaditthi?
Well, knowing like for understanding
what what your attavada is frees you
from attavada. But you can still have
craving for these five aggregates of
okay. Well, yeah, but to what extent you will
Well, yeah, but to what extent you will
only know when you're free from
attavada. Puthujana can't get accurate
representation of what craving is
present in sotapanna without becoming a
sotapanna. That's important thing to
keep in mind.
But because people's minds are used to
having it all laid out. Oh, this is what
arahat is. This is what sotapanna is.
Okay, now I'm No. If you truly
understand what it is, you'd be at least
a sotapanna. Yes.
So, that must that that criterion must
not be compromised cuz you'll end up
otherwise you'll end up thinking you
understood what arahat is but without
being one, which means there is no
understanding of it.
So, in order to understand attavada, you
need to in order to free yourself from
attavada, you need to understand what
attavada is.
And what attavada is is what I described
it to be. And even like like even
commentaries cuz Pali is clear what it
is. It's assuming an external like
so to speak. Yeah. Assuming the self
sense of self externally as in So, you
can describe to yourself
There's my experience as a whole. Call
it five aggregates. Call it whatever you
want. If something is external to it,
If something is external to it,
how could I even think of that?
How could I think of something external
to my thinking?
That's a complete contradiction in
terms. Yet, if you start looking at your
vague sense of self that you have,
ambiguous, it kind of has that property. It's
it kind of has that property. It's
completely independent of everything
that's happening to it, which means it's
not independent.
But you keep maintaining that utter
blatant discrepancy cuz you never think
about it.
And even you go to practice Dhamma,
become a monk, and that takes you even
further away from thinking about it.
You just find our niche of things you do
now. You don't do everything. You're
restrained, but you're still doing it.
And you're doing your meditation
technique, and you're doing your
methods, and you're doing this, and
you're doing this, and you're doing
this, and your responsibilities, and you
never stop and think about
contradictions that you carry throughout
all that doing. That's why you can't do
your way out of enlightenment. You
do your way out of ignorance towards
enlightenment. And you can't like keep performing
And you can't like keep performing
kamma, they will then directly they will
free you from kamma while you're
performing the kamma. You can only set
up
the right kamma, so to speak, the right
action of renunciation, saying no to the
senses, you know, becoming a monk and so
on. So, yeah, there is some kamma
involved, some acts,
on the basis of which you can understand
the nature of action.
In the same sense you need to abandon
evil by establishing the basis of good
so that you can then understand both and
free yourself utterly. Yes.
But people
silabattaparamasa is on the level of you
still assuming the connection between
you doing things
and contributing towards enlightenment.
Only efforts to understand nature of
things contribute to enlightenment, but
you'll only know how much in hindsight.
You can't tell at the time.
Only once you get the right view, you
realize "Oh, yeah, it's all those nights
I spent like thinking and pondering
relentlessly on the meaning of my
feelings or intentions, nature of
consciousness. Oh, yeah, yeah. That's
that's a direct way that results in
understanding of those very things."
But not until you understand.
And that's the simile of the the the the
the axe, the handle. Yeah.
Then after all, now I need to replace
it. I've done. Look, I used it all up,
gone. What now? Ignorance is gone.
But people
Well, they have difficulty accepting
that because it makes things much more
overwhelming because first you accept responsibility
because first you accept responsibility
for it. You accept responsibility for
not being a sotapanna, which is also
equally unpleasant.
Then the whole confusion over "So, what
do I do then?" And then it's hard to
give up
the view of
Well, more like hard to give up the
dependence on having something to do.
If you have nothing to do,
you you basically you get you get
crushed with that that nothing to do.
So, I must some do something.
And that's what I was saying to you this
morning, wasn't I?
Um
on the way back from Pin But like for
many monks,
uh
worldly doing gets replaced with what
monks do. But it's equally the same
principle, the same thing, the same
existential attitude. I do this
because if I don't do anything, I'm
going to start sinking.
Literally. Because it's so difficult to do
Because it's so difficult to do
nothing. Yeah. Like even when those
people try to do nothing, the attitude
will try to make it into something. Like
me doing nothing now becomes your
forceful doing. Yeah, you need some
external thing which would like confirm
that you are not just a loser, but you
are doing something.
Yeah, yeah, measure
Well, no, like yeah, okay, you know,
maybe I don't have the right view, but
I've been practicing for 15 years. So,
surely No, no, I refuse to admit accept that
No, no, I refuse to admit accept that
that might be might have been for waste
like wasteful. No.
No, it surely counts to something.
But maybe it was not wasted. Maybe it
just needs a little bit more and
Yeah. Little bit more. So, 15 years now
little bit more.
But if you're honest with yourself, you
realize Well, would I know how a little bit more
Well, would I know how a little bit more
help me? No. So, I'm just hoping for
magic to happen after the next step, to
win the lottery,
to get the right view. It's on the same
level, magical thinking.
I don't know how what I've been doing
relates to getting the right
understanding cuz all I've been doing is
doing of different kind. I went to this
teacher who told me to do that. I went
to another teacher who told me to do
this. Then I was doing this. I'm doing
everything now. I got my own way of
doing things, all on the level of
depending on something to do.
And then yeah, the more you invest in
it, more effort invested, the harder it will
more effort invested, the harder it will
be for you to
look at it for what it is. I still don't
know what I'm doing, and I still depend
on having something to do.
Yeah, especially if you
spent like thousands of hours in
terrible to admit that it was just a
waste of time.
Well, I think it becomes impossible to
admit. Like full on.
Like full on.
Admitting would equal
breakdown. And I want to ask
And I want to ask
another thing about this sakkayaditthi
because basically as I understand it,
that atta
is included in your experience, and your
experience is basically conditioned is
external as you say so to speak. Yeah.
So, it cannot be
See, but that's the
independent atta. Yeah, it's not but
it's not like
The reason why what you just said is not
accurate is because
even when you have a thought of what
externally conditions your experience,
that cannot be that external because of
which your experience is conditioned.
How can you experience that which is
beyond your experience unless you
experience it? Yes, yes. So, if you're
experiencing it, it cannot be external
to your experience cuz it's your
experience. Yeah, I mean external to the sense of
Yeah, I mean external to the sense of
me.
Like this is not me because
notion of external, it's internal for
you already.
Oh. And that's how you uproot attavada.
And that's how you uproot attavada.
By not leaving not giving it any way
out. Because you are always actually in
that Well, you you have no choice, of
course, but your view doesn't think
that. So, any form of allowing any form of
So, any form of allowing any form of
external, it's allowing the basis for
the for the attavada to be there. So,
can you So, see even when you say "I'm
My attavada is conditioned by external."
You already assumed external independent
of your experience, and that's the basis
for your very attavada you're trying to
undo. Ah, I got it. And so, can you always
Ah, I got it. And so, can you always
like try to catch this this kind of
point? Yeah, that's the whole point.
Keep keep bringing the point back to
your mind and then not losing it. The
point that no matter what sense of self
your yourself might be.
Lofty, far, internal, external, it's all
within the aggregates and when you think
it's all within, it's not external that
that thought of that external is already
within it. That's the thing. So, you
stop providing basis for it cuz it needs
constant nutrient. You remove the basis
then the nature of it will become
apparent after a period of time.
So, you just repeat basically the same
kind of process to like to catch this
you What's going to happen is you start
repeating it it's going to make sense in
the beginning.
But then you start doubting it. Then you
will have to find a way of getting back
to it through that doubt.
And keep doing cuz each time you start
doubting it means you're reaching to a
new level of it. Yeah. Initially a new
idea, you're so inspired everything
makes sense. You've been doing it then
that inspiration runs away. And then you
start doubting it. And you don't see.
And that's where you have to keep
pushing forward. Yeah. But the whole
point is yeah, develop the theme
that doesn't provide the basis for any
notion of external in regard to your
experiences as a whole. So, that's what
I mean. It's not like there is no
external. There is external
which is experienced by you. Which means
that external is fundamentally internal.
Very good. Because you know, I realized
one thing that you cannot make any kind
like a progress if you try to catch
these pancha kandhas these five
aggregates as as that external.
No. And the fact that you keep assuming that
And the fact that you keep assuming that
you could
means you keep allowing possibility of
external. And that in itself is already
wrong. Yeah. Because you know, I was
like watching trying to watch these
pancha kandhas, you know, like that
method and other thing that they are
maybe impermanent or whatever. But you
can't move further because you are
always like watching something Well,
your watching of pancha kandha is within
pancha kandha.
Exactly. So, assuming like assuming any form of
So, assuming like assuming any form of
out of it is the basis for atman. So,
you can't any basis So, you can't like I
will stop atman.
But what I can do is stop maintaining
this obvious contradiction of assuming
external through these little
unquestioned attitudes and habits and
thoughts. You you undo that to the sufficient like
You you undo that to the sufficient like
extent necessary, there will be no room
for atman.
And then you realize yeah, there is a
self. And that's another thing where people
And that's another thing where people
say there's no self. There's no self.
Uh-huh. No, there is self.
It's not yours.
But that thing which is self is there.
What is that thing? It's pancha kandha.
That's what the Buddha said. But people
don't even arrive at it because they
hold by the there is no self.
So, there is the external view of my
aggregates already, modern science, what
not. And then I just extended even
further with a another layer of wrong
view of saying there is no self. That's
what the Buddha said. Yes. So, you just
deny your denial even further. Yeah. Yet
all of it is assumed external to you
which means you are through and through
atman. So, first you need to admit it that
So, first you need to admit it that
there is that sense of self and then
stop putting it external to the
experiences as a whole.
Yeah. But see it within it.
Change the order. That's all all you
need to do.
Not discover new things, just keep uh
Sorry, cease
uh perverting them. Perverting the
order. Cease messing them up.
That's what a person who understood
would understand the Buddha for the
first time would say, "Oh, it's like
putting the second first and the first
second." The the Tathagata cleared it out. It's
The the Tathagata cleared it out. It's
like what was upside down now it's
proper. Yeah. Yeah.
You can say that in poetic sense. You
can say it in a very literal sense which
is exactly what it is. Oh. Oh, yeah.
Sense of self
the world it's actually sensed within
the world. Inconceivable to be outside.
Now, anybody can Oh, yeah, I I get that.
I get that. Yeah, great. Now develop
that theme day and night.
Don't abandon it.
Doesn't matter what you're going through
in your life, don't abandon the theme
that your sense of self can never be
external in regard to your thought of
external as well. I see.
And then you will be sort of literally
sucking out the oxygen
that's necessary for that sense of self
to keep enduring in that external
manner. Mhm. There is no basis for it.
It cannot
I mean, it cannot be maintained.
Mhm. So, yeah, there's nothing mystical about
So, yeah, there's nothing mystical about
it.
But there is nothing scientific about it
either. Because science is already a wrong view.
Because science is already a wrong view.
So, you need to have instruction. Okay,
this is what I need to look for.
And then you need to start discerning it
in your own experience because if I tell
you this and now you go as a as a and
make a mantra out of it and just
mechanically repeat things that I told
you you're not going to do anything.
you're not going to do anything.
And again, it's not incidental that all
these people that misquote Ajahn Chah
are also people who who praise Buddha or
Buddha meditation where you're just
repeating Buddha
rhythmically and that results in
samadhi. Yeah.
Yeah.
You know, it's
with that samadhi. It's quite amazing. I
can't figure out how you you you you
came to these conclusions by yourself,
you know, just reading suttas because
I'm also reading them but I can't see
these things. Well,
I've never been avoiding my
responsibility from the beginning.
So, that's where what you read in the
suttas start to apply
much more accurately. Yeah.
It's it's less it's less pleasant
but that's not optional.
There's no other way like you can do by
avoiding this.
You can suffer to different account on
account of it.
But it's the same thing that needs to be
done. And people who suffer on different
And people who suffer on different
accounts are people who like, you know,
have been developed sort of
like have proper samadhi, proper virtue
then you suffer less
on account of the same thing.
If your starting point even as a layman
is right there without
sufficient proper samadhi or sufficient
proper virtue, you will suffer much
more. But nevertheless, either way the point
But nevertheless, either way the point
is to arrive at it.
So, yeah, you can read all you want.
Like for goodness sake, I mean,
people get into Ajahn Chah
and completely misquote it and
misrepresent it.
Not out of malice, out of complete
misunderstanding. They have no idea what
he's talking about. Yeah, they dedicate
life to the teaching of Ajahn Chah.
And then you hear the views and it's
quite shocking how they're able to
maintain such contradiction. Yes.
Cuz he could have not have been more
blunt and more clear
in many other ways. But even that won't
make any difference if there is not even
a mundane acceptance of responsibility
and transparency in regard to your own
intentions and actions.
And that doesn't mean just yes, I'm
responsible. That means that no, I must
feel this.
I must feel this existential anxiety on
account of responsibility for things
that I don't even have a memory of.
And it's a very unpleasant state to
begin with.
And when you start accepting it, then
you realize
practice of dhamma at first is not
optional. Secondly, it's not up to anyone else or
Secondly, it's not up to anyone else or
any external pattern, form, method,
institution. It's upon me being free from craving or
It's upon me being free from craving or
not free from craving.
That's it. And that's also how you
realize the practice of dhamma doesn't
manage your suffering.
It uproots it all together. You don't
suffer in the first place, thus there's
nothing to manage, thus you're free from
any burden, any duty, anything you must
do. Why?
Why?
No reason to do anything anymore.
But you won't arrive to that through
blindly adhering to the dependence on
needing something to do
which prevents you from admitting that
you're responsible for that.
Oh, I don't hold to fixed views. That's
your fixed view.
You must not trust anything. So, you
shouldn't trust even that statement.
Does sotapanna have
suffering? Uh From arahant's point of view, yes.
Uh From arahant's point of view, yes.
From puthujjana's point of view, no.
Knowing the way out of suffering means
you can't suffer.
And that's what sotapanna is. He knows
the way out of suffering.
So, if puthujjana doesn't accept doesn't
take that as a criteria, he will then
think that he knows what sotapanna is to
what extent while still being a
puthujjana. And that's the contradiction
in terms.
Yeah. The only way to know a sotapanna
is to become one as Ajahn Chah said.
And what is that suffering which from
the point of arahant
is in sotapanna? Uh symptoms of the
illness that are left while illness has
been cured.
So, nuisance.
Nuisance. Ah, nuisance. That's what it is.
Ah, nuisance. That's what it is.
Say you're dying of cancer.
Yeah. And you know, your joints ache, your
And you know, your joints ache, your
lymph nodes are swollen, everything
hurts, everything is unpleasant.
But really,
you mentally suffer on account of you're
dying of cancer.
And now I come and I cure your cancer.
But your joints still hurt.
You still don't have hair. You still
your lymph nodes are still swollen. But
you know you're free from cancer. You'd
be quite joyous actually. You wouldn't
mind any of this discomfort.
But yeah,
from some from the point of view of
somebody who is free from even those
residual symptoms, yeah, you can say
there is some sort of suffering.
But not from the point of view of
somebody who is still in sheer terror of
dying of cancer. He He's not even
bothered by his symptoms. His only
bother is the fact that he's dying of
cancer. So, you uproot that, then symptoms won't
So, you uproot that, then symptoms won't
bother you even more
symptoms will bother you even less.
That's why sotapanna can turn away and
sort of go back and whatever.
Or or lay people can be sotapannas and
so on.
And sotapanna
Still live the life and be attracted to
sensuality and everything else. Cuz
you have uprooted the illness completely
and you fully understand that. It's not
like oh, what is happening to me? No,
you know exactly what's happening.
So, no amount of symptoms can
reintroduce the illness and that gives
tremendous confidence.
Because of which you can become careless
and complacent cuz you don't care.
Ultimately, you know that you cannot
become ill.
Doesn't matter what you do.
But he still doesn't have a full
understanding of things. No, he has full
understanding but he he has not
dwelled enough in the theme of full
understanding, not long enough.
In the same sense I just gave you the
how to approach Atavada, you must you
can't just think about the theme once or
twice. You must keep discerning it
and dwell in it for as long as it takes
until the handle of the axe wears out.
You don't know when it is.
For Sotapanna it's even clearer than
that cuz he knows exactly
what to think and what themes to
develop. He just needs to do it. That's why the
He just needs to do it. That's why the
Buddha keeps encouraging him, causing
a rising sense of urgency.
Cuz for most puthujjanas, when they
think Sotapanna it's pretty much almost
an arahant or it's basically almost like
what I am, a puthujjana.
They can't see Sotapanna for what it is.
Because of that, they're not a
Sotapanna.